I suppose I got to the stage where I should indulge in looking back as well as hopefully still looking forward to my future work
There's some people who end up as astronomers who right from the start knew what they wanted to do. I wasn't like that at all
When I was young I was interested in nature and as also in numbers but I don't think I had any conception that I might end up a professional scientist but I can think of two things that puzzled me when I was a child, which perhaps showed I had some interest in science. One was extremely mundane; I remember watching the behaviour of tea leaves in a bowl of water and when you spin a bowl of water the tea leaves pile up in the centre at the bottom
And I remember puzzling about this and it wasn't until I was a third year undergraduate, I understood why that happens but that was something that puzzled me. I also remember on the summer holidays looking at the tide tables. And not understanding fully, why high tide was different in times at different places around the coast. And there again that's something different which I'm puzzled about when I was young and of course only when I got to university did I understand the reasons for that. So I suppose having thought about things like that indicates I had the propensity for doing science and worrying about things
I turned out to be good at maths and therefore I was urged by my school to apply to study mathematics at (The University of) Cambridge, which I did but actually I have always regretted having done that because I think I would have done far better to have had a broader science curriculum
The science I have used in my career I have sort of mugged up as I went along and it was clear to me when I was an undergraduate that I was not cut out to be a mathematician. I was not enjoying it, I was enjoying the applications. And so when I got my bachelor’s degree, I thought of how I might use my talents in mathematics to do some subject where I could have a more synthetic and synoptic style of thinking. And I thought quite seriously about doing economics but I instead decided that I would, instead, do astrophysics
And this was really a bit of luck as I knew nothing really about astrophysics. I got a research grant to be based in Cambridge for my PhD and I was allocated to Dennis Sciama as my PhD supervisor and this was a bit of luck because Dennis Sciama was a most charismatic person who was in touch with what was going on and he had a very good stable of students as it were even though I was diffident about whether I was doing the right thing. Within about a year I was fairly confident that I was going to get a PhD and I was doing something that I was interested in. And that's because I was lucky that this was a time when new things were happening, the first evidence of the big bang but also the first evidence of black holes and one of the earlier phases of my work was to try to make sense of these objects and why they were radiating and able to be so bright
I was lucky in a way to be appointed a professor at a fairly early age and in my 30s I already became a director of the Institute of Astronomy for a period. This gave me some obligation to have a broad view of the subject and I appreciated that. In retrospect I feel I was not experienced enough to do a very good job in that role but I am happy that things seem to thrived an no disasters happened
In Cambridge I derived great benefit, not only from my own research, but from taking participating in the debates. I think I have been someone who enjoys collaboration and that's not just because other people do most of the work but I think, less cynically, because the subject does evolve through a collective effort. It is a collective enterprise and I have been fortunate to have been able to take part in the debates about all these subject and to see how originally speculative ideas gradually come into focus and become firmed up as a combination of new data and new ideas
Going further on in my career, I was lucky, in that, many of the issues that I started to  think about as a graduate student have continued to be the focus of my interest throughout later decades. Understanding black holes, understanding the big bang and other problems like that but one issue that really became important in the 70s and 80s was understanding the, so called, cosmic dark matter. It became clear that it was more in galaxies than the stars and gas we see. That to understand how they hold themselves together under gravity there had to be a lot more stuff producing gravity than what we see and this was one of the first evidence for dark matter and I was one of the people who was involved in some of the early work on this, so called, dark matter theory
When I was getting to the age of 60, I realised I perhaps ought to do a bit more general service to the university and things outside and I consciously tried to do something like this. But in a sense I tried too hard because I ended up having various other obligations which meant during the last 10 years I have probably had less time for full-time research than I had previously because I became the head of a Cambridge college, Trinity College, for eight years. That was very stimulating because it is a marvellous concentration of academic talent across all fields so  was very good for my education
And I also had the chance to be president of the Royal Society which is a 5 year commitment which of course, again, involves a great deal of involvement across the field of science and international contacts and I became a Member of the House of Lords in 2005. So those three activities diverted me from astronomical research and having shed them I am hoping I am not too gaga to be able to go back and spend a bit more time doing research than I did in the last decade
Another thing that I have done over the last 20 years and which I am glad to have done is to have become more involved in outreach and presenting work to the public. I have written a number of books, I have been editor of an encyclopaedia that sold half a million copies and I feel I have made a contribution through speaking and writing about astronomy to general audiences. And I think I am lucky that the subject is one that attracts wide public interest. There's a huge amateur community of course and there is a lot of intellectual interest in origins. Where did the Earth come from? Where did life start? Where did the big bang come from? In my writings I have really tried to address some of those big questions
I think it is possible to predict, one decade ahead, what we will be thinking about. I shall myself be hoping to take a greater interest in planets around stars because in my Institute here in Cambridge we have one of the world leaders in this subject joining us and we are  starting a new group in this subject. So I hope to learn a bit from that but I also hope to continue to work with colleagues on clarifying some of the issues which are still mysterious about extreme phenomena in the universe. Gamma ray bursts, black holes etc. and learning what we can from new computer simulations and new observations
I now find myself, for the first time in more than 30 years, not responsible for any institution;  I'm not head of a department or head of a college or head of anything like the Royal Society so I suppose I can be more outspoken and irresponsible in a sense. And one thing which I hope to do as well as continuing with my science is to get involved in some political issues that I care about and get involved through various campaigning organisations and through the House of Lords